[Music]
Averell until i recently brought out a
few films about david icke and london
real and there's so many different
topics that they raise censorship free
speech the growth in conspiracy theories
the recent planned emic film blew up a
few days ago and that's even even bigger
than the david icke interview so I felt
kind of overwhelmed with all of those
different threads to follow I thought
the best thing to do would be to talk it
through with my friend Peter Limburg who
he's done a lot on this topic with his
intellectual Explorers podcast and also
recently we put out the film culture war
2.0 with him on rebel wisdom so we look
at all of these different topics and
especially kind of try and dig into what
is good journalism good sense-making
in this environment this kind of liminal
space that we're all in which peter has
called the liminal war just just for the
topology of the conversation what what
are your what are your thoughts I guess
my first question would be what are you
hoping to get from a conversation like
this yeah I put out those three films
last week and there's so many different
angles to them there's so many different
kind of questions about sense-making in
the liminal space that we're in there's
the massive topic of conspiracy theories
that is kind of exploding right now
there's this sense of kind of the
reaction of like the big tech platforms
there's the relationship between
conspiracy and sense making and it's all
the things we've been talking about in
the channel for a very long time like
how we use discernment in this kind of
digitalized age to make sense of things
rather than relying on truth and the
sort of the broadcast mainstream blue
church apparatus to make sense of things
and all of these different ways of
making sense kind of in cut in
competition and clashing with each other
like I don't know what the answers are I
don't know what the solution is I don't
think anyone knows what the solution to
finding truth in the new
decentralized environment is I've talked
about this kind of interregnum period
where we've lost the sense making blue
church apparatus and we were basically
whether we realized it or not we were
offloading a lot of our sense making
capacity to that structure so blue
church being the establishment that was
constructed after 1945 that includes
hierarchical Authority it's a generally
broadcast model it obviously includes
all of the the main media organizations
and now we're having to reboot from from
scratch but we're doing it in a really
kind of haphazard way and and really
like rebel wisdom has been about at
least from the the middle of last year
rather than the content itself it's like
what's the process that we come to
making sense of the world and how can we
improve that how can we improve our
discernment how can we how can we catch
ourselves lot locking into like
certainty and certain explanations how
can we rest in uncertainty and weigh
things up and this area of conspiracy
theory more than any other seems to have
that quality of like this is the truth
and then and then a real attachment in a
sort of pseudo religious way and I also
feel it really difficult to talk about
it because there's so many different
things like the word conspiracy is such
an overloaded term there's like
alternative narratives of which some of
them have more truth than others and
it's used as a way of kind of dismissing
anything that it sort of deviates from a
mainstream narrative but then you've got
another factor in there as well which is
where I feel like there's a qualitative
difference between alternative
narratives of things that have happened
like the Kennedy assassination but
particular events and then this kind of
all-consuming explanation for everything
which a friend of mine was talking about
recently and he said and I it feels like
a qualitative difference to me like
those two things and what
can slip into the other very quickly and
very easily but why I wanted to come
into this conversation with you is that
I know you you've run the intellectual
Explorers Club you've dealt with these
topics a lot you've probably gone more
deeply into it than I have and I have a
sense that the right way to proceed is
in this inquiry rather than a kind of
this is what I think modality one of the
criticisms of the piece that I thought
was was right the Brian Rose piece was
look fuller is just trying to set
himself up as the as the judge and jury
and it's like yeah that's not that's
obviously not a that's not gonna work
like even though even when I'm doing
that kind of talking to camera it's not
a definitive statement but there is
something about the nature of the nature
of YouTube the nature of of broadcast at
all
feels like it feels like a definitive
statement and as soon as you make a
definitive statement you open yourself
up to be criticized and that's fine
that's the process and that's a process
of coming to truth but it also feels off
in some way I think we have to find a
new way of of sense-making in this
particularly in this liminal space what
we need is some kind of some kind of
rules of engagement or some kind of some
kind of I don't know decentralized
method of like I don't know maybe like a
yeah like a code of conduct or like a
set of principles or something that that
more people can sign up to if I have any
any any sort any kind of certainty it's
that certainty is wrong like anyone who
has any kind of certainty about what is
going on right now and who's behind it
and what's really like that feels like
an all encompassing explanation I'm
immediately suspicious of because you
just get into this let how do they know
that if you actually listen carefully
and with discernment when lots of people
are speaking and lots of people who are
getting massively kind of up regulated
right now and you listen with
discernment you think
how do they know that okay they may have
expertise in this particular area but
they're asserting things about Bill
Gates Falchi like these vast
conspiracies it's like they don't know
they have no greater insight into that
than anyone else so that was delicious
everything you said there's like so many
threads that are coming to mind right
now that we can go down I first wanted
to say two things that came to mind when
I watched your latest three videos or
rebel wisdoms latest your videos is that
one that when you're talking to that
camera that one were you're talking the
cameras like the first one you did that
I got fired up saying that I got there's
like I got through most like kink my
body that's when I reached out to you
because I've been like away from the
rebel ISM family for like the last two
months cuz of my own project but I got
inspired to get plugged back in after
seeing that and then that's why when I
reach out to you yesterday that's why
we're here we just want a you see like I
said let's do this as had this
conversation that's one thing I just
wanted to mention the other thing I
wanted to mention was that how I
appreciated your approach because it was
like hyper nuanced and there's no easy
answer that you presented like you know
the big tech companies like Brian Brian
rose and like the tension that you have
because you like him on one extent but
then you see his personal faults and I
actually felt your tension there
I felt the nuance when you were talking
about it and it felt authentic to me so
I just wanted to appreciate that and I
think we need more of that so that being
said I have I have a desire to like kind
of just go down the the confusion your
confusion the unknowingness there just
get the color and taste of it but maybe
that a more prudent question is why
like let's maybe go down a little bit
more though why the conspiracy theories
stuff captured your attention initially
and you already touched on it but as you
know there's a lot of battlefronts in
the culture war what I'm kind of dubbing
the little war now and there's something
there about like the potency of
certainty that the conspiracy theory
narrative has so maybe you can kind of
speak a little bit more on that yeah
yeah it's a good question
the simple answer is that they are like
I'm a journalist and they are as far as
I can tell the most newsworthy
phenomenon right now like if you if you
know anything about the way we make
sense of the world you realize that
especially right now where we have an
almost infinite amount of information
you can kind of make note pretty much
any narrative that you want and you
follow these rabbit holes down and you
kind of either persuade it by something
or not persuaded by something so just as
a phenomenon it's it's quite
extraordinary and then it also plays
into all of these wider topics of how we
make sense of the world at all why we
think something is true rather than
something else being true
the psychological basis for a lot of
this stuff and then why I feel it's so
difficult to talk about is one that
there's so much charge around it like
people are really charged up about these
topics and there's a kind of religious
dimension to them like there is a
religious dimension to it on some level
and that isn't to say again that isn't
to make any judgment about the truth
claims and so you you get so my
uncertainty is tied to this feeling of
it's very difficult to talk about with
nuance because if you if you can fall on
one side of sounding like you're saying
you just need to sort of trust the
mainstream narratives and any
alternative explanations are bullshit or
on the other side of giving too much
credence to stuff that is kind of has
seems to have very little basis in in
reality so you've got that kind of knife
edge thing so I think that the right
place to sort of the right place to hold
is like how are we making sense
what is our how is a discernment being
challenged where are we collapsing into
certainty and fixed narratives rather
than holding a balance of probabilities
a lot of things that sort of frame
themselves as searching for truth and
I'd say like the planned emic film
is the most obvious example of that
recently is sort of framed as revealing
the truth is also like highly
manipulative highly partial highly is
this weird sort of dynamic of we're
going to help you find the truth and
it's our truth it's this truth like that
that feels like a very complex thing to
to unpack like it doesn't feel the whole
thing on all sides feels like it's
taking people's agency and people's
discernment away because it's and it's
part of the as we've talked about a lot
on the channel this sort of sense of
game a dynamics game a being the current
system that we have the underlying
source code that we have gained B being
any potential other system being
accelerated with exponential tech and
especially in the field of sense making
what we're seeing is like the most
sticky the most powerful mimetic
artifacts being accelerated increasingly
fast it feels like the pandemic is a is
a catalyst for all of the worst things
about the game a society weaponized
attention selecting for the most
powerful most sticky most compelling
certain narratives and nuance and
discernment is really under threat while
at the same time you've got this kind of
mainstream perspective which actually to
me doesn't really feel like the
mainstream anymore it feels like it's
just one thing among many and that
mainstream perspective is being
challenged hugely because lots of things
that from the beginning of the crisis
have been sort of like well that's just
a conspiracy theory the idea it could
have come from a lab is a conspiracy
theory right now there's really for me
quite compelling circumstantial evidence
at least that it did like it seems to me
at least as probable that it came from a
lab as it came from a wild
origin and that's what that's one
example but you've got this kind of like
sense of the mainstream like that when
people say well the mainstream feels
like a conspiracy theory right now that
it's true the mainstream does feel a lot
like it comes like if you're just accept
like the blue church is really buckling
under the strain of novelty and under
the strain of the this sort of sense
making overload that is going on under
the under the impact of the virus so
it's like all it's a it's a incredibly
difficult to hold picture and I think as
I kind of tried to unpack in the in the
first film I think our way as
certainties of making sense just aren't
up to it
free speech absolutism in an environment
where attention is finite and
distraction is infinite while the
consequences of misinformation and the
consequences of getting things wrong now
take on a son of life-or-death quality
while also the necessity of challenging
some of those narratives as well is also
important and then you've got this kind
of simplistic collapse of for example
YouTube saying we will only accept stuff
now that goes along with the w-h-o
guidelines and it's like have you have
you not seem like what the w-h-o has
been doing like how in hop to China
they've been saying that you shouldn't
wear masks I mean the whu-oh is has said
some pretty crazy things yeah when you
were talking the the word dangerous
comes to mind and actually like kaffir
kind of just went through my body a
little bit talking about this knowing
that this potentially could be broadcast
and the rebel wasn't channel it's like
oh how's this gonna be interpreted and I
like that kind of distinction where
there's like you know the conspiratorial
aspects of the blue church and then the
whole kind of kind of conspiracy
narrative q and on all the stuff is
coming online
and how do you talk with nuance there
without pissing either of them off like
for me with the the stuff I used to do
with the culture war analysis it's like
I really like to take the principle of
charity writing where I passed that
ideological Turing test in such a way
where I can map out a proposition
of a memetic tribe or a person in such a
way that they feel completely understood
and then so you just you just be a
method actor with their ideology so to
speak and also kind of to sink in what
do they feel like on a felt sense level
when they believe to be true what they
believe to be true right and if you can
do both of those things you can really
talk to someone most people don't do
that
so I like having the Omega rule and all
that type of stuff with a Medic tribe
but if you do that you're gonna get
trouble with the blue church if you do
that with the conspiracy theory stuff
because then you're just one of them
right and so that's not good at you get
canceled the big tech companies could
ban you and YouTube all the type of
stuff alternatively criticism is
important you know those just being a
performative agnostic is not a panacea
you got to actually challenge people's
truth claims because people are wrong
and if you do that with the people with
the conspiratorial because there's there
is signal in the noise but there's a lot
of noise but if you challenge it with
this sort of like religious intensity
you're one of the bad guys you're one of
the shells you know then they're gonna
come after you so it's like you're
damned if you do damned if you don't
hear and it feels like a very very
dangerous game to play especially when
you're sense-making
in a broadcast sort of way which rebel
wisdoms doing so I feel what you're
feeling right now we're potentially
feeling all right I think I feel what
you're potentially feeling yeah I mean
it feels like I try to personally put
out stuff that I feel that I can defend
that I can agree with and I can stand
behind but what I feel like my
particular perspective on this is is how
do you how do you retain the best of the
values of the the existing structure
which at its best was was functional
like journalism at its best where it's
really aiming at truth and it's looking
to get both sides of the story and is
offering people the right to reply so
you're not putting out stuff without
putting it to them first which I tried
to model in the in the it was more of a
sort of show don't tell well I can I can
tell people like this is how you're
supposed to do these things but I think
it's far more
valuable to demonstrate what good
truth-seeking looks like there was a
there was a functioning system that
became corrupt it became corrupt it
became hollowed out like increasingly
hollowed out but when it worked and
probably the last time it worked
properly in America right so is probably
like the 1970s you had like journalism
had a really important function of
holding power to account and it it was a
you had a small number of media channels
so if you were asked to go on that media
channel you would have to go on it and
if you didn't go on it and you as a news
P as a news person would say we asked
the government if someone was available
and they said no one was available that
would that would sting that would kind
of be empty chairing someone we're now
in this kind of almost infinite media
environment where there's no real
consequence of people to go on some and
not go on others
it's accelerated the point where people
are not asking difficult questions
because they're worried that that person
isn't going to come back on their
channel and that's the that's the same
so that's a failure condition of the
alternative media but it's also a
failure of the mainstream media now
because there are so many more outlets
for for everyone it's very hard even
when you don't have any sort of
established truth seeking environment
it's very hard then to hold people to
account and need to be held to account
because I think good truth seeking again
slipping into kind of the jargon that
we're familiar with
I think journalism and academia
practiced in the way they are meant to
be practiced is actually a game B
Enterprise like it is it's a truth
seeking enterprises and game a is all of
the forces that have captured that truth
seeking enterprise I think Brett and
Eric talked about in the Rubin report
really well as the truth-seeking cannot
survive an encounter with market forces
but that's why I think the a lot of the
conspiracy theories the instinct is
right it's kind of like Bret again talks
about religion being metaphorically true
and fat and literally false I
I don't fully buy that I think a lot of
Christians are very upset about that
definition but I think there's some
truth in that and I think there's some
truth in for me a lot of the more
extravagant conspiracy theories are
metaphorically true and literally false
and I think they're metaphorically true
because we are in a completely
dysfunctional system that has rotted
from the inside out for all of these
systemic reasons I think I've heard
people use the the thinker baudrillard
to explain it as kind of his idea of
simulation that any structure becomes a
becomes hollowed out once you establish
it as a structure if it was a
truth-seeking structure what you end
what ends up happening is that you get
people who are maneuvering within that
structure for other reasons other rather
than truth and it becomes increasingly
hollowed out and I think that especially
in America is what we're seeing and I
think a lot of people are perceiving
that a lot of these structures have
essentially become hollowed out that's
the civilizational threat that I think a
lot of people are picking up and I think
a lot of them are sort of miss miss
diagnosing it so you and I spoke often
about like playing chess with council
culture mm-hmm and like cancer culture
is usually associated with social
justice activists or the social justice
warriors or the world purity and it is
interesting I think they used to have a
lot of momentum in culture war 2.0
before firk Ovid now they're kind of a
conspiracy theory stuff I think that is
the mimetic tribe that has the momentum
now and I would also argue that every
single mimetic tribe especially like I
would say most mimetic tribes are
disembody tribes in the deepest sense I
think they all have their version of
castle culture so it's like what I was
mentioning before is like that the blue
church tribe you know they have their
castle culture so if you don't like
signal hard against these conspiracy
theory stuff then you're gonna cancel by
them the conspiracy theory stuff if you
even criticize them one inch you know
you're gonna get canceled by them so
there's the cancer culture threat exists
across the board with all mimetic try
so and that's the kind of a skill set to
have like playing chess with cancer
culture and I think you know you and I
out of anyone pretty good at it so far
it's not not like I would what I see
when I read a lot of mainstream
treatments of conspiracy theories is
this kind of necessity of virtue
signaling to the audience to say like
every other line is this conspiracy
theory that has no basis in fact like
and you have that feeling I know if I
was to write something for one of the
mainstream mainstream organs if I didn't
put that in it would be put in by the
editor like they have to constantly
signal to everyone else in that Network
like it's a kind of virtue signaling to
say we know this is not true oh and by
the way we need to reinforce that there
is no link between five gene Corona and
just make that absolutely clear but with
that kind of old-school journalism
there's like a felt sense level of like
knowingness even if they're right and
even if they're earnest for the truth
there's this felt sense of knowingness
and it's just it kind of annoys me where
I think in order to be this was new
world especially in this sort of
in-between space that we're in we got a
return to Socrates you know the only
thing I know is I know nothing and
really build an intimate relationship
with unknowingness and I think if people
don't have an intimate relationship with
unwillingness with unknowingness with
uncertainty annoyingness they're gonna
run into narratives that provide that
certainty so that's another question
that's coming up for me right now is how
do you earnestly sense make as a good
journalist in this liminal war when
you're you're trying to be accessible to
people who don't have a good
relationship with unknowingness like I'm
the practicing stoic as you know and
then I like I like Jordan halls kind of
uh I'm repurposing Jordan halls kind of
phrase and putting it as the axiomatic
goal of stoicism if you will is being in
right relationship with reality and if
you're in if you're going to be in right
relationship with reality you got to be
in right relationship with everything in
reality including emotional states and
realities
uncertainty of unknowingness and I think
if you don't have if you're not in right
relationship with that state you're not
comfortable with swimming in that state
when you need to swim in it then you're
gonna run into these unhealthy and
pathological forms of knowingness and so
I guess the if we can tease out a
question there is how do you sense make
in a broadcast medium when the people
that are going to consume your artifacts
don't have a good relationship with
uncertainty or annoyingness well the
first thing that comes to mind is we're
all going to have to develop that like
the I think it was Jamie wheel who used
the Buckminster Fuller quote at the
beginning of one of his lectures our
task is primarily metaphysical it is to
spontaneously develop the behaviors that
will avoid extinction and I think that
is one of the primary ones is developing
that relationship with with uncertainty
and also that it's a it's a it's an
existential project for sure like it's
an existential project to develop that
in ourselves and to to because I because
I think if we don't I mean I I go as far
as to say I know that if we don't that
this trajectory were on right now is
going to be self extinguishing because
because we are so easily weaponized on
one side or the other of different
questions and then we're like that sort
of polarization and tribal ization
around these fixed identities the only
way out of it is to be able to to pull
up to another level where you can see
complementary truths and understand that
they both hold essential values like the
right and the left which I think we both
agree is kind of a not a particularly
helpful framework for understanding the
world right now like the value of self
responsibility and of loyalty
accountability self empowerment that the
right holds
has to be balanced with care empathy
that that the left holds and actually
that the right has a different form of
care and empathy that looks different
from the left so all of these but it but
it yeah but it's more of a kind of
individualist like that that there is no
I we have to come out of these either/or
situations there is a concern about kind
of this these conversations being too
exclusive because of the terminology
that's being used
I was wondering it would actually be
quite good to put together a glossary of
terms for the sort of broader may be a
either rebel wisdom glossary of terms or
a you've got good coinage game like
we've we've kind of we've given you
props in the past for having good
coinage game and I think you even came
up with coinage game as well as one so
you even got good coinage game at
creating coinage game like you come up
with some very good sticky heuristics
like your culture war 2.0 piece I think
was really really useful for that
like the liminal war gray pills and
mimetic mediation in particular the idea
that what's required is some kind of
mediation between these different
mimetic tribes who've coalesced around
different perspectives all of that is
super important and super useful and I
think yeah if anyone's watching this and
wants to help on putting a glossary
together then I think that could be a
good artifact to put out there for
people to to dive into we haven't come
up with a good like this thing whatever
it is this this space that I'm in that
you're in and various other people are
in it is a thing but none of us have
come up with a particularly useful word
for it game B is one sense making web is
another probably the sense making web I
think is my favorite of all of the yeah
I like the sense making web as well
there's like all these adjacent sort of
like this game be the meta modern is the
post rationalist but the kind of the
sense making web kind of second umbrella
term for all of them in a way that's why
I view it
every every Sunday at the store we have
a mediation campfire with Jason Snyder
and Jared Jaynes they have the both end
podcast and it's basically a memetic
mediation podcast and so the three of us
we just gather around the digital
campfire and is just talk about magnetic
mediation with a bunch of people and
last session was pretty good like poke
me at the edge of my thinking they're
thinking about mimetic mediation what is
the goal of it really because there's
this sort of instinctual pushback from a
lot of nomadic tribes is the both sides
ism argument or the all sides ISM
argument like what are you saying
everyone's just equal you got to find
the middle ground between the two and
like nope right like no so for example
like one of our friends Jessica she's
like a really good faith feminist but
Jessica in a conversation was some kind
of like a woman-hating insult Melissa to
actually have a conversation
propositional II and even like like
emotional harm on Jessica side hands
down right so it's not going to be
somewhere in between in my opinion if
they have a conversation but if the goal
of memetic mediation is to get into
right relationship with each meme with
each tribe then maybe you know Jessica
will move down you know a you know a
little bit the the inside will move up a
lot and then maybe they'll find
themselves in the right relationship but
if you can somehow figure them figure
out how to get them to the table and
that is like you know you almost won in
a way if you can actually get them to
the table and sit down and allow them to
get in that state of unknowingness
together
and so why I brought that up is that
we're talking about like what makes a
good mimetic mediator and Trust you know
it's like the capacity to not just
appear but to be trustworthy and to
model a certain behavior and that's what
I like what like just a circle back to
the appreciation I had for your nuance
is that that engendered trust like when
I saw you I started trusting you
I already trusted you but like you know
like I if I didn't know you I would have
felt I had the felt sense of trust there
and so what's coming up right now is
maybe
the way in order to approach this
existential project is to model being
trustworthy in this liminal state and if
that's the case how to do that yeah it's
like daniel trachtenberg have talked
about in the in the war on sense making
piece doing sense making like this the
solution for the problem of truth and
the problem of sense making requires a
huge amount of intimacy it requires a
huge amount of like honesty and
wrestling in public and another thing
that a few people have said is like show
me the people who are wrestling with
things in public don't I don't want to
see people who are certain about
anything right now I want to see people
who are clearly going through the
process of wrestling with difficult
polarities that cannot be reconciled and
also that the intimacy thing is putting
stuff out there that is vulnerable as
well as like talking about your own in a
process of what's going on when you're
coming to these conclusions or not
conclusions and saying I feel uncertain
I feel and also if you fuck things up
say look I fucked that up
like I don't for example just taking a
taking a an example now it's like Brian
Rose I don't see a way back for him
unless he's prepared to say actually I
fucked up the the worse angels of my
nature got got me and and I III did some
things that I wasn't completely honest
about this I wasn't completely honest
about that but I did it because I'm
passionate about this thing and I
believe or whatever whether whatever we
don't want to speculate about his real
motivations but it fascinates me how the
sort of stuff that you and I and and
rebel wisdom and many of the other
people that we know in this space like
we've most of us have got some kind of a
grounding in some kind of inner work a
and interpersonal dealings whether that
circling or whether that's authentic
relating or all of these different
things it's like and that requires
immense emotional honesty and emotional
intimacy to actually have those
conversations and I think what we're
reaching towards is some kind of way of
doing what we've done in those
interpersonal contexts in a public forum
around some of these bigger like
cultural topics so this is really good
and we don't know how to do it yet so
I'll share I'll be intermittent sure
like a personal story and I think I
shared it with people for well share
with with this audience is that before
quote covet could happen I received some
like bad news personally I won't almost
share it now but I already shared it
with you and it's about two months ago
now and I was devastated right I was
just like laying on the sofa having like
an existential crisis and the thought I
came online is like what do I do now
with my life I had no idea what to do
with my life and there is judgment
around that like I read so much books
that all these spiritual practices all
these goal-setting methodologies and I
don't know how to live my life right now
and they were shamed there and then the
adjacent thought emerged like hey no one
else knows how to live my life either
and then that kind of like allowed me to
see the shame and it's sort of like just
disappeared and then being a good stoic
and wanting to be in right relationship
with reality I'm like okay how do I be
in right relationship not knowing how to
live my life and this is sort of like
starting to build an intimacy with
unknowingness and I started my journals
on the letter platformer I'm just being
radically honest and what's coming up
there is maybe this is a clip I think
John and I mentioned it in our
conversation we had in Toronto so maybe
you could play this clip as well in one
of our circling sessions because John
and I and Luba Muir and a few other
people
Lubin readers on the channel as well we
were having a biweekly circling group
authentic relating practice group in
Toronto and then John had this like
really profound insight he said that in
order to be someone's peer you not only
have to have the capacity to peer
through them
but you have to allow them to peer
through you and that's sort of like what
we're talking about about just sort of
like modeling this this this behavior
and I think this is exactly what we're
doing right now
we you and me kind of just putting
ourselves at the edge of our thinking
here publicly being a little messy not
knowing where we're gonna go what's
gonna merge but people see this and
they're like okay I imagine people see
this like okay these people aren't that
bad right they're not like bad faith
actors and another thing that came up
was that I like the word of the intimacy
and also let's not be shy about being a
little seductive right because really I
feel like I'm up for grabs right now I
feel like narratives could seduce me and
I'm open to that reality and possibility
especially if they're truthful ones and
so being up for grabs while you're this
radically honest and truthful unknown
state is kind of seductive certainly
your honesty and authenticity resonates
with people that for me was one of the
failure conditions of this like the IDW
project was a that I didn't get a sense
of that authenticity or that kind of
sense of people really wrestling it's
really hard to show vulnerability when
you have people who either do or you
suspect might weaponize and use that
against you like it's a really it's a
it's kind of an easy thing to do when
you don't have a huge profile it's a lot
harder to do when you do have a huge
profile and I think that's one of the
things that attracted me and attracted a
lot of people I think to Jordan Peterson
originally was this sense that you did
see him wrestling in real time with
things like you you got he was the in a
way that I think that was why he was
such a perfect intellectual for the
digital ages that you sought you felt an
intimacy with him and he felt him
wrestling with what was going on with
him and I remember once I saw him kind
of musing on on
one of his Q&A is about how he was
feeling a lot more defensive and a lot
more reactive around some of the press
interviews that he was getting and he
talked about it as a as a corruption of
his soul and I was like that's that's
really that's the kind of honesty and
the kind of personal willingness to
share his own personal process that I
think was why he was so successful and
why a lot of people felt this real
connection to him and I don't think I've
seen that I can't think of many other
people who've done that I might be wrong
there may be others yeah I agree I think
Peterson's a different beast in that way
and you know so like you know and I
mentioned this on my journals now and
still I haven't mentioned this publicly
like rebel wisdom but he was my
therapist for two years before he became
famous and you know so I have a great
love for him he helped me out but I will
I guess I will criticize him here if you
want to call it criticism I do agree
with you that he has this sort of like
radical form of truthfulness like the
Kathy Newman interview just displayed
that with brilliance and you did a
documentary about that and people
haven't seen that before like what's
going on here and then the blue church
she has like agents and stuff right now
so I call him like is it that Pacific
bouncers that he has from the blue
church I imagine they have a hard time
containing a guy like Peterson fully
because he's so committed to his
truthfulness muscle but when I have a
sense that I could be wrong here it
could be uncharitable but he doesn't
always come from a place of love
especially when he's criticizing the
social justice activists or whether I
don't feel he's coming from a place of
love and those moments and I think in
order to be intimate and possibly
seductive there's nothing wrong with
being so doctor especially if it comes
about organically is being truthful in
this state of unknowingness with love
mm-hmm and this is was it like when I
did the the workshop but rebel wisdom
when I was in the men's group in in
London which is brilliant it's not just
about the mind is about the heart
I want to speak from the heart just as
you're speaking from the mind and if you
can do that then people will hear yeah I
mean I I agree I think in the second
interview I did with with him I did ask
him I did push him a little bit on on
that like his reactivity towards the
sort of social justice warriors or and
this this sense of also because he
argues himself that I people don't have
ideas ideas have people so if that's the
case why why the aggression towards the
people can we have that compassion
towards people despite the fact
disagreeing with their actions and
despite the fact that we may disagree
with that their thoughts and their
beliefs so yeah I think I mean I'd agree
with that I feel something I think I
have said before I would like to put out
another another film about the looking
back on those two years of this sort of
the the Jordan Pederson phenomenon which
we all hope is not complete but sort of
just looking on that at that trajectory
some of the the people who criticized
him and and I'd love to do it with an
interview with with him I don't know
whether that's possible or or not but I
felt I have had some criticisms and some
concerns and I felt that it would be in
some sense I think disloyal or unfair to
do to put out those criticisms without
putting them to him personally then we
we have put out some films on honourable
wisdom that have been critical and and I
made sure I sent them to him personally
I sent them to him and Tammy but this is
a couple of years ago now but but I felt
like I wanted to do that and a really
yeah really upfront way and he responded
well to those like that they responded
well to those and took it in the in the
spirit to which it was intended as far
as I know so yeah yeah I'm the buter
Singh
you know situations another thing that
is so hard to speak with nuance just
like I was just a conspiracy theory
stuff you know it's hey and if you do
damned if you don't take things yeah I'm
glad we did this I felt like it was the
the right format to start articulating
some of this stuff because it's quite
hard it's really hard as well to when
you're articulating something difficult
for the first time yourself it's you
come up against like the broadcaster in
me and that the kind of perfectionist in
me wants it to be perfect and it's very
difficult for it to be perfect when
you're kind of still in the process of
thinking about what it is you actually
think and how it needs to be framed so
yeah I feel I feel like just but in the
process of articulating a lot of it kind
of lands and and you you learn what you
think while you're speaking a lot of the
time so this is this is another part of
this of this question that you asked
before about what is what is the nature
like the nature of this enterprise has
to be real-time sense making and
articulation of things that may not have
been fully you certainly I mean other
people probably ever have expressed it
far better than then I can and have in
this conversation but we all need to be
at the edge of our thinking at the edge
of our articulation where we're actually
trying to find the words for it as where
we're talking that's that's the nature
of the I'm really clear that that is the
nature of the exploration that we all
need to go on is to bring ourselves to
that edge because the the systemic
crisis that we are at the beginning of
is going to be
like I think we're all perceiving all of
us in this space of perceiving that it's
this is it this is the this is the
hopefully the phase shift but
potentially something more catastrophic
and the only what none of us know what
the what the world on the other side of
it looks like the only way to get there
is by articulating in real time and
trying to trying to yeah trying to tune
in to what wants to emerge through us
yeah yeah and I feel like I'm sort of in
it now when I was just observing the
culture war like kinetic tribes but I
actually want to get tribal now I want
to be I think I'm gonna find my tribe
the embody try and then the pure sense
or the fight communitas I think that's
where the beauty is and that's where we
have to be truthful or to get there and
then before we go that I just wanted to
like just say something about well you
it's almost like that kind of like what
you said about your perfectionist desire
and and then you know like the pressure
that you put on yourself produce really
really good content it puts you in a
position out of the sense of making
web-like rebel wisdom a lot of people's
eyes with a cool standard you knows a
lot of good stuff out there and we know
all the players in the space we're
friends with them but you guys you know
you put yourself in a situation where
you have most eyes on you in a way and
it's almost like you know the cliche
line like with you know great power
comes great responsibility and it's like
now you're in a situation this liminal
war we're almost sacrificing that sort
of that that perfectionist tendency in
front of others it's like an act of
sacrifice it's like the zone hero's
journey that that you're on here which
at which I find quite delicious
if true well who knows I mean the danger
of all of this is is inflation and not
being held accountable and and all of
these things like I mean I do feel that
like I certainly in myself feel that
sense of real okay this is this is what
we've been
building up - we've all had this sort of
sense of this was coming
whatever this was this was coming we
didn't know it's gonna be a pandemic but
the but this sort of sits this his
system was was on overload and this
something like this was going to happen
and so yeah I feel that sense of
alignment that sense of like real
urgency and that sense of kind of it and
we all need to find that if like is is
like if not us who really what what
while also being aware that there's the
risk of inflation and the risk of
bullshitting ourselves and the risk of
why all of those things come in as well
well let's take Brian Rose as an example
like that to me is like perfect example
its inflation it's getting caught up in
some kind of archetypal struggle of only
seeing sort of one side of the coin and
I think it's a it's a we see it he's not
the only one like it we see it a lot
it's like that for me is a really tragic
trajectory it's identifying oneself with
one side of an archetype it's it's it's
allowing the inflation its kind of the
manic energy of the moment and being
overwhelmed by the manic energy of the
moment and then the ego grasping onto
this rather than allowing it to pass
through and thinking that we like this
messianic fervor that comes in as well
we talk to like psychedelic narcissism
all these sort of things it's like being
aware that that's that's a part of the
territory as well and like I think if
you have this your primary relationship
with others is asymmetrical via
broadcast media then I think you can get
captured by ego very easily but I think
with with us like we've talked about ego
before being captured by ego and we
might have different conceptions of ego
but I think you can get in right
relationship with ego in such a way that
you are still ambitious enough to make a
difference in the world but you don't
identify it
completely in order to be kept in check
in a trust comes to mind like do we
trust our people our tribe our audience
to keep each other to keep us in check
like I trust you to call me out on my
bullshit and you have and I think you
trust me to call you on your bullshit
which I have right so we trust each
other there and we're not submitting
each other to each other because you
know we want to be nice or likable or
whatnot and I think that's what's needed
and not only modeled sort of this
transparency and truthfulness with
ourselves but also in dialogue OHS and
dialogue together yeah yeah this is a
whole new I know you have to go so this
is a whole new topic but but all I'll
say on that is like I don't think people
realize just how how important that is
and how much it's required like that we
all like the amount of work the more
that I've got into sort of personal
growth work and accountability and all
of that the more I've realized like that
never ends like in any in any good
relationship and I think that's what we
need within the sort of I don't think
we've got anywhere near enough of it in
the in the web of people that we're
talking about I think there's way
there's way too much proxying of
authority to some key nodes there's way
too much lack of kind of accountability
and willingness to kind of test our
ideas and test our own bullshit against
each other there's not enough
communication there's too many people
who are who just don't have any concept
of what this kind of path of growth and
a growth looks like and back away from
from anything that feels like it
challenges their their personality or
their ego structure it's right now
you've got a you've got a fucking steer
into it you've got to go into the fire
and I think it's only those of us who've
done quite a lot of that in a work that
realize just how difficult that is and
how much how much we need to to steer
into that yeah that's what that's all
I'll say because that could be a whole
nother topic
and I'll end with this that now that it
seems like we're patting each other on
our backs is feel free to call us on our
bullshit whoever's listening right now
yeah yeah well thanks that was fun
yeah it's always a pleasure man and yeah
keep on doing give a shout-out to the
stoah that you've been running and
putting your heart and soul into since
the beginning of this so you're you're
creating a place for people to come
together and do all of this work so it's
really great to see that yeah each go to
the www store dad CA you can check it
read about it they're cool mantle we'll
catch up soon what you are rebel wisdom
was set up to make sense of the world at
a deeper level than the mainstream media
it was built for these times of crisis
and change which is why we want to do
what we can to meet the challenge of the
times more films and also for our rebel
wisdom members weekly sense-making calls
with our amazing interviewees and also
we're introducing the wisdom gym a place
to practice some of the skills that
we've talked about on the channel thanks
for watching see you soon
you